Bettie Carmack

Shannon, AL 35142 | (205) 435-9779 | Cycadese1@fastmail.fm

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

A dedicated legal professional who holds a Juris Doctorate in Law in the State of Alabama and Georgia with a demonstrated expertise in legal research, writing, investigation, and court appearances. Proven success in building trusting rapport with clients and offering sound legal advice in clear and universal terms.

SKILLS & COMPETENCIES

- Westlaw/Lexis Nexis Research expertise
- Brief writer (criminal appeals)
- Brief writer (Constitutional Defense)
- Investigator
- Brief Writer (Inmate Litigation)
- Special Reports/Motion for Summary Judgments
- Statutory Interpretation Analysis
- Microsoft Teams proficient

05/2021 - Present

08/2003 - 05/2021

Outlook 365 proficient

LICENSES & CERTIFICATIONS

- Alabama Bar License; Georgia Bar License
- Administrative Civil Prosecutor licensing boards and agencies
- Notary Public for the State of Alabama
- Certified Guardian Ad Litem

WORK EXPERIENCE

The Carmack Law Office | Birmingham, AL

Family Law Practitioner and Consumer Defense Attorney

- Represents private clients in child support matters and divorce matters;
- Handles tenant/landlord matters;
- Handles consumer rights matters;
- Handles collection and debtor matters;
- Investigates claims of discrimination; and
- Investigates claims pursuant to Title IX.

State of Alabama Attorney General's Office | Montgomery, AL

Administrative Prosecutor/Licensing Attorney and Prison Litigation Attorney (02/2006 - 05/2021)

- Represented the State of Alabama, governmental officials, regulatory boards and agencies, and judges in all forms of civil litigation covered by the Alabama Department of Risk Management;
- Developed a specialty in: §1983 excessive force cases (immunity defenses, statute of limitation, failure to state a claim, lawsuit barred by the bankruptcy automatic stay, etc.);
- Prepared summary judgment motions, dismissal motions, and appeared in federal and state court as first chair in prison litigation lawsuits involving medical care, excessive force, and deprivation of prison essentials;
- Wrote appellate briefs that have resulted in arguments being presented in the 11th Circuit, Alabama Supreme Court, and Alabama Court of Civil Appeals; and
- Represented State boards and agencies in licensing matters and disciplinary matters.

Appellate Attorney (08/2003 - 02/2006)

- Prepared legal briefs in defense of the State of Alabama, particularly in the areas of direct criminal appeals, federal habeas corpus petitions, and post-conviction petitions (Rule 32); and
- Organized and maintained all case files, using Pro-Law and other systems, pursuant to the requirements for the State of Alabama

EDUCATION

University of Alabama School of Law | Tuscaloosa, AL ---

Juris Doctorate: Law

- Associate Editor of the Law and Psychology Review (Bobbitization of Sex Offenders)
- Public Interest Law Grant Recipient

University of Alabama | Tuscaloosa, AL

Bachelor of Science in Accounting

Honors Graduate, Commerce Executive Society, Beta Alpha Psi (Accounting Honorary), Gamma Beta Phi (Service Honorary)